Okay, so today's daf is צדי ב. Tzadi-Bet. We pick up at
the bottom of צדי א עמוד ב Tzadi-Aleph Amud Bet and we
are going to almost finish the פרק perek today. And so we're
dealing with like we have some sort of, you know, I call
more fun סוגיות sugyas here at the end. It's all fun. Anyway,
we're going we're picking up with continuing the Rabbi Akiva's response to
this person who did this trick to try to prove that he
was exempt for or should not pay a heavy fine or a
heavy בושת boshet more literally for uncovering this woman's hair. So Rabbi
Akiva said well, you know, because he showed that she did it
to herself. So he says look, you're not allowed to injure yourself.
And that led to a fascinating discussion yesterday about whether a person
was or not were or not allowed to do self-injury.
Certainly if it's, you know, if it's something that will not heal,
then that's minimally בל תשחית, Bal Tashchit, you know, and suicide certainly
is אסור asur but a self-injury that will heal is that or
is that not allowed and the גמרא Gemara sort of said it
was a debate it was not really clear in the end what
the, you know, where the exact prohibition was from. But even if
you're not allowed you still have to if you do it there's
no payment if somebody else does it to you you have to
pay. And the other example Rabbi Akiva gave was cutting cutting down
shoots like young saplings you're not allowed to do it but if
you do it to your own property you're exempt, somebody else does
it to you they have to pay. So why are you not
allowed to cut your own saplings? So let's take a look. בל
תשחית Bal Tashchit you already yeah it said that. So I mean
we brought that concept in yesterday. So that's where we pick up.
So צדי א עמוד ב Tzadi-Aleph Amud Bet about eight lines down
in the wide lines
והקוצץ נטיעותיו Hakotze Netiotiov by the two dots. Okay. So it says
like this. תני רבה בר בר חנה קמיה דרב. Tani Rabba Bar
Bar Chanan kimei deRav. So Rabba
Bar Bar Chanan taught in front of Rav. שורי הרגת Shori haragta
if I go ahead and I say to Michael, Michael, you killed
my ox. נטיעותי קצצת Netioti katzata or you cut down my saplings.
And then Michael says back to me, אתה אמרת לי להורגו Atah
amarta li lehorgo sure, because you told me, you asked me to
kill your ox. אתה אמרת לי לקוצו Atah amarta li lekoto you
asked me to cut down my saplings. פטור Patur Michael's exempt. Okay
now. So well, one minute, well, okay but let's take a look.
I mean well, that's a good question. Is there any evidence? אמר
ליה Amar lei so he first thought that it meant that I
actually brought witnesses that Michael did it. And that Michael's still able
to say that you told me. So he says, אם כן לא
שבקת חיי לכל בריה Im ken lo shavta chaya lekhol birya you've
not allowed the creatures to live. כל כמיניה Kol kemei does Michael
have any any נאמנות, ne'emanut, any believe you know, any trustworthiness in
his claim? I have evidence that he did it or we thought
I have evidence that he did it. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
איסתמיא istamya okay this was a ברייתא Beraita argument you're saying it
doesn't make sense. Should I strike it out? Should I erase it?
Throw out this ברייתא? Beraita? So אמר ליה, amar lei, לא, lo,
no, you don't have to throw out the ברייתא. Beraita. לתרגם מתניתין
Letargem matnita your ברייתא Beraita could be explained in the following context.
בשור עומד להריגה ובאילן עומד לקציצה. Beshor omed lahariga ubeilan omed leketzitza.
Now it doesn't say what Michael said which could have just been
that there's no evidence to it. But if there's no evidence then
it's like a boring statement. Then Michael's right. It's a classic כופר
הכל. kofer hakol. You owe me a hundred dollars, no I don't.
Okay. So the case is I do have evidence, okay, but and
so why does Michael get off? Because the circumstances indicate that Michael
is probably telling the truth. Why? Because the ox had to be
killed. Okay and why I don't know why it was a goring
ox שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal then it would be בית דין Beis
Din that would have to kill it. It was sick maybe, okay,
something like that. The the saplings had to be cut down, you
know, they were blemished, they were blight, whatever it was. It was
clear it had to get done. Okay. So so in that case
and then so it makes sense that Michael that he's telling the
truth. So גמרא Gemara says, okay, אי הכי מאי קא טעין ליה?
i hachi mai ka ta'ein lei? So
if that's true then what what type of compensation would I be
asking for anyway? The the job had to get done. So it's
not like that thing is worth anything.
No. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אנא בעינא למיעבד האי מצוה. ana bina
lemevad hai mitzvah. No, I say to Michael, I'm not asking to
compensate me for the ox and the saplings but you stole this
מצוה mitzvah opportunity from me. So what מצוה mitzvah opportunity is it?
דתניא Detanya let's take a look. Okay. So first of all where's
this idea of of stealing a מצוה mitzvah and that there should
be some type of a compensation? Okay now by the way let's
look at רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says the example of what what
the cases are that it had to be killed. So עומד להריגה
omed lahariga רש"י Rashi says שור שהזיק. Shor Sheheis. Now he doesn't
say שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal because again a שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal
would be בית דין's Beis Din job to kill it. But maybe
it would be like, you know, like the the mad dog, you
know, the you know, it's just a damaging thing and for the
public welfare I have to get rid of it. Okay and what's
a tree that has to get cut down? עומד לקציצה, Omed leketzitza,
אשרה. asherah. It's a it's been worshipped as a as a god.
או כל עץ O ko etz
no, not you didn't worship it. Someone whatever I don't know I
bought the land from some pagans who had worshipped the tree. So
first thing I gotta do is clear down all the אשרות. asheras.
Okay. או כל אילן הנוטה לרשות הרבים O ko etz hanoteh lirshus
harabbim or it is endangering the public it's leaning over the רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim and it's about to fall ומתירא שמא יפול על
אדם וימות. umisyarei shema yipol al adam veyamus. So the מצוה mitzvah
here would be to remove potential injury, damage from from from you
know from the רבים, rabbim, to save the רבים rabbim from the
risk of of injury. Okay, so that's you know a minimum you
know מצוה mitzvah of השבת גוף, hashavas guf, protecting people's person and
property and person. So therefore, I wanted to do that מצוה. mitzvah.
So so where's this idea that you can sue somebody for stealing
a מצוה mitzvah from you? דתניא, detanya, we saw in a ברייתא,
braisa, ושפך וכיסה. v'shafach v'chisah. It says you shall you shall spill
the blood when you שחט shecht you know an animal like like
a deer let's say, and cover it with blood. מי ששפך יכסה.
mi sheshafach yechaseh. So it's the same person. The one who spills
the blood, the one who slaughters the animal, has the has the
מצוה mitzvah of covering it. So we're telling this as background for
the following story.
ומעשה באחד ששחט, umaaseh b'echad sheshachat,
so I I I שחט shechted the animal, וקדם חברו וכיסה, vekadam
chavero vechisah, and Michael, he ran and said, oh look, there's a
מצוה mitzvah to do, and he ran and he covered the blood
with with with dirt. He did the מצוה mitzvah that was really
my responsibility. וחייבו רבן גמליאל ליתן לו עשרה זוזים. v'chiyivo Rabban Gamliel
litten lo asarah zuzim. So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said, we'll transport
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel 2,000 years to the future, Michael, you gotta
pay Dov 2,000, 10 זוזים, zuzim, 10 gold coins, you stole his
מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, how do you come up with that assessment? Right,
and how does that applicable? So I'll talk about that in a
second, but anyway, but so the point is here, I'm saying to
Michael, Michael, you did it, you stole my מצוה, mitzvah, and Michael
says, well, you asked me to do it. So again, it's now
now so not clear is this idea of stealing a מצוה, mitzvah,
why is he believed in this case? But whatever it is, we
assume that the circumstantial evidence is such that even though it is
my מצוה mitzvah to do, it's not exactly the מצוה mitzvah of
covering the blood, it's a job to do and it's reasonable that
I would sort of like ask somebody to do it for me.
So in this type of a context, there's not enough basis to
collect for this stealing of the מצוה. mitzvah. Now the question is,
what is this whole idea of stealing of the מצוה? mitzvah? By
the way, there's a גמרא Gemara that asks, the גמרא Gemara treats
this story in more than one places, like it's applicable, like it
wasn't a one-time punishment that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel did, that it
really is applicable to other cases. So the גמרא Gemara wants to
know, is the problem that he stole the מצוה mitzvah or did
he stole the ברכה berachah that went with the מצוה? mitzvah? So
the גמרא Gemara said, what's the difference? So it says, well, let's
say I honored Michael with the ברכת המזון, birchas hamazon, we're all
sitting here and benching, and David jumps in and he leads the
ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon. So does David have to pay Michael 10
gold coins or 40 gold coins? Because he stole four ברכות berachos
from Michael. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara actually asks this question and
take a look here at the תוספות, Tosafos, okay? And let's take
right, take a look, he gives a real case. Okay, it says
like this.
I think it's also depend on how many people is there. For
like 1,000 people, it's much more of an honor too.
All right, right, but here we're sort of treating it as a
flat thing. But anyway, so if you take a look at תוספות
Tosafos three lines from the bottom of תוספות, Tosafos, like a third
of the way in, ומעשה באחד שקראו ש"ץ לקרות בספר תורה, umaaseh
b'echad shekaru Shatz likros b'Sefer Torah, somebody was given an עליה, aliyah,
okay? ובא אחר וקדם וקרא, uva acher v'kadam v'kara, and somebody else
jumped in front of him and he stole the עליה aliyah from
him. Okay, so does he have to pay the guy he stole
the עליה aliyah from עשרה זוזים? asarah zuzim? ושאלו לרבינו תם, v'shaalu
l'Rabbeinu Tam, they asked רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, so what's the story?
I he stole my עליה. aliyah. ואמר לו שיתן לו תרנגולת לשחוט
תחת אותם שתי ברכות. v'amar lo sheyitten lo tarnegoles lishchot tachas osam
shtei berachos. So there are two ברכות, berachos, right, the ברכה berachah
in the beginning and the ברכה berachah at the end. So not
10 זוזים, zuzim, not 20 זוזים, zuzim, give him a chicken. Which
is basically like a type of a, you know, like a make
him happy. Okay, just give him something to to you know, you're
right, you did something wrong to him, appease him, give him a
chicken.
It was not an auction off
עליה. aliyah. What's that? Auction off עליה aliyah because he said that.
Well, that's true. Anyway, right right. רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam did not
want to apply the גמרא's Gemara law. He wanted to just make
שלום, shalom, okay? ואין לו לריט"ם זה. v'ein lo l'Ri Tam zeh.
So there's no, you can't say like, you know, that you can
like, you know, just make the guy happy. דאם כן מה חייבו
רבן גמליאל עשרה זוזים, d'im ken mah chiyivo Rabban Gamliel asarah zuzim,
like what do you do with the גמרא Gemara treats this 10
זוזים zuzim as a real thing. ועוד פטר רבינו תם, v'od patar
Rabbeinu Tam, but רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam came up with a better
reason to get to say you don't really owe him the money.
Why? משום שיענה אמן. mishum sheyaaneh Amen.
Ah, okay, Michael, David stole your עליה, aliyah, but you can say
אמן Amen to David's ברכה. berachah. דגדול העונה אמן יותר מן המברך.
dgadol haoneh Amen yoser min hamivarech. And the one who says אמן
Amen gets more שכר sachar than the one who makes ברכה. berachah.
It was
clear רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam did not want to apply the law
of the גמרא, Gemara, okay? He was trying to just make שלום
shalom and move on. Okay, and then he has another reason. Thank
you.
ועוד אמר רבינו תם דבבבל אין דנין מילתא דלית ביה חסרון כיס.
v'od amar Rabbeinu Tam d'b'Bavel ein danin milta d'leis bei chisron kis.
Nah, we don't deal with cases that you know, that it's not
a real financial loss. You remember the גמרא Gemara before? Even if
it's not technically a קנס, knas, right, if it's not a real
financial loss, we don't deal with it in בבל. Bavel. So you
didn't lose any money, even though you lost a מצוה. mitzvah. Right,
but the person who did it, did it had the same. Right.
Right. Well, yeah, probably. That's an interesting question. So anyway, so this
leads, the רא"ש Rosh responds to this and the רא"ש Rosh says,
like he now רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam never said it was a
קנס knas because if it was a קנס, knas, how do you
apply an arbitrary קנס knas that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel assigned in
one place to other cases of ברכת המזון, birchas hamazon, of cutting
down a tree. But the so it seems like
The ראש Rosh says,
hold on,
yes so he quotes רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, he says it's middle
of סימן יד, Siman Yud Dalet, you don't have to look, I'll
just read it: דינא הוא וגמרינן מיניה. deina hu vegamrinan minei.
The fact that the גמרא Gemara applies רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel shows
it's not a קנס, knas, it's a real דין, din, and we
apply it to other cases. ועוד אי לאו דינא הוא מה שייך
למיקנסיה גברא דלמצוה קמיכוין ואנן ניקו וניקנסיה? ve'od ilav deina hu mah
shayach lemiknesei gavra delmitzvah kamichavein ve'anan neiku u'niknesei?
And anyway, like if it was a קנס, knas, why would you
give a קנס knas to somebody who was trying to do a
מצווה? mitzvah? Of course he was trying to steal a מצווה, mitzvah,
it's different. Anyway, so basically the ראש Rosh emphasizes this is like
a דין, din, this is not a קנס. knas. But it's really,
you know why I find this fascinating, because okay fine, it's a
דין, din, what type of a דין din is it? I mean,
you could say it's דינא דגרמי, Dina DeGarmi, there's but what we're
trying to do, and here's why it's really important for contemporary examples,
you know, sometimes פוסקים poskim do discuss it in a מצווה mitzvah
context, like the whole question about, this comes up in the, what
do you call it, in the halachic literature, is if I honor
somebody to do the ברית מילה Bris Milah for my son and
then this, and then somebody else jumps ahead and does the ברית
מילה, Bris Milah, whatever. So I imagine that type of circumstance. But
anyway, so these types of cases of stealing מצוות mitzvos come up
and they do discuss things like this רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam case.
But why I find it more fascinating is if you don't think
it's a קנס knas and the גמרא Gemara does think whatever it
is, even if it's a תקנה, takkanah, not a קנס, knas, it's
something that then we can apply to other cases. What it's trying
to do is give a, treat as theft or damages and give
a dollar value to something which is abstract and not concrete, right?
The right to do a מצווה. mitzvah. Normally we say מצוות לאו
ליהנות ניתנו. Mitzvos lav lehenos nitnu. It's not something that has a
dollar value in הלכה halacha and so on, and he's just saying
you still stole something from the guy, nothing physical, you or you,
you know, and you robbed him of it or you damaged something,
I mean, stole is the more precise. Now why is that relevant?
Why do you think that's relevant nowadays to think that the גמרא
Gemara is trying to do that? What exactly?
To make this a valid damage, to give to treat as stealing
when you didn't steal something physical, you just stole something abstract. Copyright.
Exactly. The big problem in הלכה halacha is that the whole world
of, you know, intellectual property and copyright and you buy an Artscroll
סידור siddur and they write a million times it's absolutely forbidden from
the law of the תורה Torah and the law of the, of
the government to make any photocopy, blah blah blah blah blah, right?
So okay, what exact law of the תורה Torah makes it אסור
assur to make a photocopy of the Artscroll סידור? siddur? Okay, so
how where do we get intellectual property, intellectual property rights? So it's
a real question in הלכה, halacha, but it's an interesting to think
of something like this as a somewhat precedent, you know not obviously,
I don't know if people, I don't know if I haven't heard
of anybody using this, they try to get it through other ways.
But it is interesting because it's not, this is a מצווה mitzvah
that's, you know, but the point is it's showing I think חז"ל
Chazal trying to treat as property as a thing you stole from
somebody something that is not a physical object. Yes Ze'ev.
This is a very concrete language question. Should we erase the ברייתא,
brayta, the word יסמיה, Yisamye, יסמיה, Yismaye,
what's what's that?
I mean I read it יסמיה, Yisamye, but yeah, but anyway, but
I think of it like the word סומא Suma like blind or
make it erase it. Yes so it's erase it,
makes it blind of no one will see. It should be we
blind to this.
Yeah I'm not big the exact grammar. No one will see it,
erase it, yeah that's what I think it is.
So another practical question because you know like things like these arrays.
So like you know someone gets married right? You're going to get
a thousand and one dishes, so should I not טובל tovel a
dish because then I'm taking away the מצווה mitzvah of them going
to the מקווה? mikvah?
Well, before you've given it to them, before you give it to
them, it's not their מצווה. mitzvah. After you've given it to them
and they have their dishes that are standing and ready to go
to the מקווה mikvah and you want to run and do it
for whatever. I mean, a lot of people would be very grateful
for it, you know. So there's I mean there's whatever there's circumstances
where you could assume that somebody wants me to do it, you
know. On the other you know, but on the other time the
גמרא Gemara says you know that people would rather do a מצווה
mitzvah themselves than have somebody else do it for them. But we
all know there's circumstances where that's not true, they'd they'd be very
appreciative. So obviously it depends on the circumstance. Okay, let's move on.
So it is for the ברכה bracha you're saying like.
Well no, that's a debate in the גמרא Gemara that hasn't been
reconciled. So anyway now the גמרא Gemara continues, which is the reason
that I quoted which is so fascinating is because it's about cutting
down these saplings. But now we get to this issue of the
משנה Mishnah that you're not allowed to cut down even your own
saplings. That was a tree that had to be, that was gonna
collapse, that you had to cut down. So let's take a look.
אמר רב Amar Rav said רב, Rav, דיקלא דטעין קבא, dikla de'ta-on
kava, if you have a palm tree that produces a קב kav
of fruit, whatever that is, a bushel whatever, I don't even know
what a bushel is. אסור למיקציה, Assur lemikatzya, you're not allowed to
cut it down. Now we haven't even, he's giving some type of
a quantification to the משנה Mishnah but we haven't even explained what
the problem is. You know, the problem clearly clearly is בל תשחית,
Bal Tashchit, particularly because it's a tree you're cutting down. Okay? You
remember yesterday we applied the idea of בל תשחית Bal Tashchit to
like just ripping up clothing.
But there's an interesting question whether, if it's so פשוט, pashut, you
know, whenever you know, you know when you were, you know, for
me at least in childhood, your mom always said, you've got to
eat all the food on your plate, it's בל תשחית. Bal Tashchit.
That's the Jewish mother's version of their children starving in Africa. It's
בל תשחית, Bal Tashchit, okay? So, the, I mean, you know, you
could ask an interesting question, is forcing myself to eat something when
I'm not hungry less of a בל תשחית Bal Tashchit or you
know, less of a בל תשחית Bal Tashchit than throwing it out?
Like, you know, you're not wasting it whatever anyway. But, okay, so
the point though is we're all, we're all raised to believe that
בל תשחית Bal Tashchit sort of applies, you know, for all things.
But it's not so clear, at least in the תורה Torah it's
very specifically and concretely about the idea of cutting down
a tree, right?
To a little bit yesterday the חידוש chiddush was that we applied
that idea to ripping up garments. Okay, but that clearly is the
problem when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you're not allowed to cut
down your own trees. So, although it has yet to be explicitly
articulated, so the גמרא Gemara is trying to quantify when is it
really considered to be השחתה, hashchasa, like destruction? Right? I don't know,
like let's say I want to, you know, plant something else here,
let's say I don't like the view, let's say I mean there's
always the question, what exactly is the context
of wanton destruction? But if you're talking about a tree itself, you
know, it might be, it might be not be as easy to,
you know, to say that it's מותר, mutar, right? When you abstract
it, okay, oh you're not allowed to wantonly destroy, so all you
have to say is it's not wanton destruction, right? If I want
to tear up these garments because it is a way of for
me relieving my grief,
then it assuages my anger, then it's not wanton destruction, right? If
you know, if I want to have a water park and I
use a million gallons of water to go down a water slide,
is that בל תשחית Bal Tashchit of water or that's the way
I have some fun and it's entertainment? It's very hard to do
a real בל תשחית, Bal Tashchit, you say, right, unless you're really
doing it just for the purpose of destruction and serving no other
purpose. But when you're dealing with the tree, you're dealing with the
case in the תורה, Torah, right? And it says don't destroy the
tree. So there you might think that the parameters of בל תשחית,
Bal Tashchit, you know, it's harder to say that that's מותר, mutar,
right? So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to
is the issue about the destroying of a fruit tree, right? That's
exactly the case in the תורה. Torah. Don't destroy the fruit tree.
רק עץ אשר תדע כי לא עץ מאכל הוא אתו תשחית. Rak
etz asher teda ki lo etz maachal hu oto tashchit. So to
give me a היתר heter to destroy a fruit tree might require,
you know, more restriction, more criteria than just normal בל תשחית. Bal
Tashchit.
And the opposite, לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, right? It may not be
אסור... assur...
right, it's a good point, it's a good point, it's a good
point, yeah.
And we can
מחלק m'chalek and say, well,
it depends if this is an actual, if the tree would fruit
at this
point.
Well, exactly, so let's take a look. That's why the גמרא Gemara
discusses how much fruit is the tree producing? So it seems like
the initial discussion of the גמרא Gemara is, if we identify it
as a fruit tree, we've got some serious problems. What makes it
a fruit tree? Right? How much fruit does it have to produce?
So let's take a look. אמר
רב,
Amar
Rav, דקלא דטעין קבא, dikla detayin kava, if you have a palm
tree that produces a קב kav of dates, okay, אסור למקטציה, assur
lemaktezeh, then you're not allowed. That presumably is an עץ מאכל, etz
maachal, you know, that produces, it's a fruit tree.
Even with that whole big tree and only get a קב? kav?
A קב kav a year, I guess, right, but even that small
amount, right, that's important, right. This is not a large amount, that's
a small amount. Even if it only produces a small amount, it's
still a fruit tree and you can't cut it down. מיתיבי, Meiteivei,
I'll ask you on this, כמה יהא בזית ולא יקצץ, kamma yehei
b'zayis v'lo yikatzeh, how much should there be on a, on a
זית, zayis, if to produce that you shouldn't? Now, again, yeah, it,
it shouldn't, actually no, I don't know if דטעין tayin means that
it only produces that in a year. דטעין tayin could mean, it
could mean that it's what's on the tree right now. I think
that that's probably more, more the literal sense of it.
It holds, it holds.
No, but it right now is suppose, is holding that amount. How,
how do they translate it there?
Bears. Bears, well, bears is ambiguous enough. That does sound like bears,
bears annually, bears right now. Yeah, that perfectly captures the ambiguity. Okay,
anyway, מיתיבי, Meiteivei, I'll ask you on this, כמה יהא בזית ולא
יקצץ, kamma yehei b'zayis v'lo yikatzeh, how much should there be on
the olive tree, that sounds like 'on' right now, and you shouldn't
cut it down? רובע, Rova, a quarter of a קב. kav. So
it's not a קב. kav. You said a קב. kav. Different trees,
שאני זיתים דחשיבי, shani zeisim d'chashivi, olives are important, so even less
gives it significance. Okay. אמר רב חנינא, Amar Rav Chanina, so לא
שכיב שבחת ברי, lo shchiva Shivchas bri, my son שבחת, Shivchas, that
was his name, did not
die, אלא דקץ תאינתא בלא זמנה, ela d'katz teenata belo zimna, he
cut down a fig tree before its time. So, obviously there's a
powerful metaphor here, the tree was cut down before its time, he
was cut down before his time.
ולא קצה חרובא בשבתא דשבתא? v'lo katzta charuva b'shabbasa d'shabasa?
Oh, that was not him. Anyway. אמר רבינא. Amar Ravina. So anyway,
obviously this is talking about, it’s not just a prohibition. It’s because
that’s what there’s like this terrible sort of symbolic significance of what
that means to destroy something in its prime and when it can
still produce and so on. אמר רב חנן. Amar Rav Chanan. אמר
רבינא. Amar Ravina. ואם היה מעולה בדמים מותר. v'im haya me'ula b'damim
mutar. Ah, but actually, until now it seems like we’re just saying,
if it’s an עץ מאכל, etz ma'achal, if it’s an עץ עושה
פרי, etz oseh pri, then it’s always אסור, assur, period, right? It’s
not about an abstract בל תשחית. bal tashchit. If it’s a fruit-bearing
tree, don’t cut it down. Now we’re going to abstract this issue.
No, no, no, actually, if you can make more money by cutting
it down and selling the wood than you can make by having
it produce the fruit, then it’s not בל תשחית bal tashchit and
then it’s מותר. mutar. So now we’ve gone from the very concrete,
now we’ve abstracted it. If actually it makes financial sense, then it’s
not בל תשחית bal tashchit and then it’s מותר. mutar. ואם היה
מעולה בדמים מותר. v'im haya me'ula b'damim mutar. תניא נמי הכי. Tanya
nami hachi. רק את העץ אשר תדע. Rak et ha'etz asher teda.
I’m sorry, what does that mean?
Meaning like if you can make more money
net-net with the annual fruit or like I’ll have fifty years of
fruit from this tree?
Yeah, that’s a good point, you’re right. How do you exactly assess
that? But how much is getting fifty years, how much is getting
a thousand dollars over fifty years compared to getting a hundred dollars
right now? So I don’t know, that is a good question. But
the point is you’re right, I don’t know exactly how you would
do the math, but the principle is clear. The principle is that
if it makes financial sense, you’re allowed to do it. Right? If
I can cut, let’s say I can cut down this tree and
that’ll allow me to plow this whole field with wheat and I
can make a lot whatever because I get the trees out of
the way. Okay, so we’ve now abstracted it. We went from concrete
to abstracting it, it’s about whether you’re doing it, whether it’s wasteful
in the doing of it. Okay, תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi
מעולה בדמים, me'ula b'damim, the field as opposed
to because you’re not just selling the tree now, but in your
example,
I’m assuming once we’re abstracting it, you’re right, it is different. It
is different. It’s not just saying that the tree itself is being
used in a better way, you’re saying I’m getting the tree out
so I can make more money. So it’s a good, yeah, you’re
right. So it’s not clear we would necessarily go that step. תניא
נמי הכי. Tanya nami hachi. ותניא נמי הכי. v'tanya nami hachi. רק
את העץ אשר תדע Rak et ha'etz asher teda זה אילן מאכל.
zeh ilan ma'achal. Now this is the פסוק pasuk that says when
you’re allowed to do it. רק את העץ אשר תדע כי לא
עץ מאכל הוא אותו תשחית וכרת. Rak et ha'etz asher teda ki
lo etz ma'achal hu oto tashchit v'charata.
If you know that it is not a fruit tree, then you
can cut it down. So the גמרא Gemara says actually we’re going
to read this פסוק pasuk to say even if it is a
fruit tree you can cut it down. Okay, so there’s the complete
taking the concrete part of the פסוק pasuk and making it a
pure abstraction. Okay, so let’s take a look. רק את העץ אשר
תדע Rak et ha'etz asher teda זה אילן מאכל. zeh ilan ma'achal.
A fruit tree also you can cut down. כי לא עץ מאכל
הוא Ki lo etz ma'achal hu זה אילן סרק, zeh ilan srak,
that’s a barren tree. Okay, either one you can cut down. So
the גמרא Gemara says we sort read the first half without the
second half of the פסוק. pasuk. וכי מאחר שסופו לרבות כל דבר,
v'chi me'achar she'sofo l'rabot kol davar,
in the end you’re going to say you can cut down even
a fruit-bearing tree, מה תלמוד לומר כי לא עץ מאכל הוא? mah
talmud lomar ki lo etz ma'achal hu? Why does the תורה Torah
say if it’s not a fruit-bearing tree? להקדים סרק למאכל. l'hakdim srak
l'ma'achal.
No, to tell you that you have to prefer a barren tree,
or
a not-just-right-now-barren non-fruit-bearing tree to a fruit-bearing one. So that allows for
the abstraction, meaning you can’t just wantonly, if all things being equal
you don’t destroy the fruit-bearing tree. Okay, so but it’s now taking
you from the concrete of the תורה Torah never destroy a fruit-bearing
tree, only destroy these trees, to saying just you can’t do something
that’s wasteful. So you have to choose between the two, you choose
the אילן סרק. ilan srak. יכול אפילו מעולה בדמים, yachol afilu me'ula
b'damim,
maybe I should have to choose the אילן סרק ilan srak at
least give some concrete meaning to the פסוק pasuk that at least
if I have both I would have to choose the אילן סרק
ilan srak even if I could make more money by cutting down
the fruit tree, the fruit tree’s wood is better? No, even then
you can cut down the fruit tree. תלמוד לומר רק. talmud lomar
rak. No, it’s a limit. So even this idea of preferring the
barren tree is only in limited circumstances when the even if you
have both in front of you, you only have to prefer the
barren tree if it makes the more financial sense. But if you
can make if the fruit tree by cutting it down is you
make more money off of it, you can cut down the fruit
tree. So this is like brilliant where you see, to some degree
this is what בבא קמא Bava Kamma has been, these concrete cases
in the תורה, Torah, an ox gores an ox and we abstract
it. But here you really have like a complete re-reading of the
פסוקים psukim that say no, never fruit-bearing, yes barren, to say really
just don’t be wasteful. Make the choice that is not the non-wasteful
choice. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
שמואל אייתו ליה אריסיה תמרי. Shmuel aitu lei arisei tamrei. So שמואל's
Shmuel's sharecropper brought him dates. אכל, achal, he ate the dates. טעם
בהו טעמא דחמרא. ta'am behu ta'ama d'chamra. He, there was a little
wine taste in it. אמר ליה מאי האי? amar lei mai hai?
Why does where did it get this wine taste from? אמר ליה
ביני גופני קיימי. amar lei beini gufni kaimei. Oh, because the palm
tree
is it’s growing amongst some vines, presumably in a way that it
wouldn’t be
כלאים. kilayim. Anyway, אמר, amar, he said, מכחשי בחמרא כולי האי? mach'shi
b'chamra kulei hai? Is it so much injury... The vines that it's
drawing their flavor? It must really be injuring the, you know, vines,
the grapes.
So למחר אייתי לי מקורייהו. Lemachar ayisei li mikoraihu. Tomorrow, I'd like
you to bring me like the the beams of, you know, of
this tree, cut down this tree. Okay, because it should, it cannot,
it should not be damaging the vines. Now, it sounds like it's
damaging his own vines. Now, he might just have been making, by
the way, a, you know, this is like, okay, this is financial
sense. Like the presence of the palm tree is causing me way,
it's got to be causing me a loss in terms of what
the grapes are producing. So here, by the way, Michael is the
example. You're cutting down the palm tree not to make more money
off of the wood of the palm tree but to, so you
shouldn't have a financial loss somewhere else. So it shouldn't have the
injury of the vineyard. So again we are continuing to abstract it,
cutting down a fruit tree if that's what makes financial sense. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says...
But there are two fruit trees sort of.
Right, right. I mean, there is the vine, right, but presumably it's...
The vine is worth more.
That's true. I don't think it's because it happened to be. I
think it was if it was injuring a wheat field, you'd also
be allowed to cut it down. But you're, but Michael is right
to point out that that's going one step further. It's not just
you're making more use out of the tree, you're just making more
financial sense. Okay, רב חסדא חזא תאלי בי גופני. Rav Chisda chaza
talei bei gufnei. רב חסדא Rav Chisda saw a, also I think
this is a palm tree growing amongst the vines, the
grapevines.
אמר ליה לאריסיה... Amar lei laarisei...
how does it translate?
Sapling, yeah, right, a date sapling or whatever a palm sapling. אמר
ליה לאריסיה, Amar lei laarisei, he said to his sharecropper, אקרינהו, akrinhu,
tear out the palm tree. Okay. גופני קני
דיקלי. Gufnei kani diklei. With grapevines you can buy a lot of
palm trees. דיקלי לא קני גופני. Diklei lo kani gufnei. With palm
trees you cannot buy a lot of grapevines. Okay, so clearly the
grapevines are the more valuable asset, rip out the palm tree. So
a very nice little discussion about the abstraction of בל תשחית. Bal
Tashchit. Okay, now we mixed back to the משנה Mishnah and back
to issues of
חבלה. chabalah. Okay, אף על פי שנותן לו, Af al pi she-noten
lo, even if you pay... oh wow, look what time it is.
Even if you pay the damages and the immediate context was בושת,
boshet, embarrassment, shame. Okay, אין נמחל לו עד שיבקש ממנו. ein nimchal
lo ad she-yevakesh mimenu.
You are not forgiven even if you make compensation until you ask
for forgiveness. This is a very important point, right? You know, it's
sort of like makes us think about יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right?
It's like, okay, I made good, I injured him, I paid off
the debt. No, what the משנה Mishnah is saying is that that's
only financial compensation. Okay, there's a lot more, you know, of all
of the sense of like being hurt and injured and, you know,
this sort of psychological injury that is not being addressed and that
you actually need to gain forgiveness for that. Now the interesting question
is because of the immediate context is coming right after a discussion
of בושת, boshet, of shame, and בושת boshet you could say in
particular, right, you need to ask מחילה mechila for. Let's say, I
don't know, let's say I accidentally... I mean, let's say I stepped
on Michael's foot, you know, and I accidentally caused him, you know,
a broken ankle or whatever, sprained ankle, he had to be out
of work for a few days and so on. Okay, so I
paid him for the loss of the work, it was a little
bit of suffering, it was not a big deal, and I paid
him whatever money. Do I have to ask him מחילה? mechila? Now
you would say, yeah, you should, you know, I mean, you still
hurt him,
but it's not the same degree as publicly shaming him, right? So
it's interesting that this משנה Mishnah occurs... Let me give you another
example. Let's say I totaled Michael's car and I gave, you know,
and I bought him a... paid him full value, he got himself
a brand new car. Do I have to ask מחילה mechila if
I damage his property and I compensate him for it? Right? So
the גמרא... Gemara... this comes right after the idea of shaming somebody.
There it's like clear you should have to ask מחילה. mechila. But
there's a whole range of cases where it would be important to
know, right, if how much is the גמרא Gemara saying, even if
you pay you should, you still need to ask מחילה. mechila. It
doesn't ask...
you're saying not talking just about בושת, boshet, it's talking about any
injury.
This comes after the בושת boshet discussion, but I'm asking that question.
Let's see where the משנה Mishnah goes. Right? Because it's one thing
to say it in the בושת, boshet, would you say it in
an injury without בושת, boshet, would you say it in injury of
property? Where would you say compensation is not sufficient? Okay, yes, Dov?
I was just wanting to know if it's the same Ferrari as
he was ever driving in כתובות? Ketubot?
Good question. Okay, so unless it's just that
the person before they were taken to court
they weren't apologizing necessarily, and now they're putting in the context of
because you're found guilty you should apologize. Not coming from his own...
I'm not sure. I think that even when it says אף על
פי שנותן לו, af al pi she-noten lo, could be you're נותן
לו noten lo of your own, like it doesn't sound like you're
resisting the process. It's just saying that besides compensation you need forgiveness.
אין נמחל לו עד שיבקש ממנו ein nimchal lo ad she-yevakesh mimenu
שנאמר... shenemar... so let's see what the evidence is in terms of
my
question. ויתפלל בעדך וחיה. Veyispalel Ba'adecha Vechayeh. וחיה. Vechayeh. ועתה וחיה. Ve'atah
Vechayeh.
So this is by אבימלך, Avimelech, so God says, return the man's
wife, שרה, Sarah, and he will pray for you and you will
and you'll be forgiven. So you see he had to ask presumably
to get אברהם Avraham to pray for him, אבימלך Avimelech would have
to appease אברהם. Avraham. Now the מהרשא Maharsha also points out that
it says in the פסוק, Pasuk, it says that אבימלך Avimelech gave
him צאן ובקר, Tzon U'vakar, right? He gave him money. So actually,
so the מהרשא Maharsha says maybe that's sort of the parallel too.
He actually paid him, gave him something, of paying him for this
financial, you know, some type of financial compensation, and nevertheless he had
to ask אברהם Avraham enough appease אברהם Avraham that אברהם Avraham would
be willing to pray on his behalf. If you're willing to pray
on somebody's behalf, it means that, you know, you've made peace with
that person, right? To get to that level. So in addition to
pay to giving him that money, he had to get him to
the point where he would be willing to pray for him, to
pray for him. ומנין שאם לא מחל לו שהוא אכזרי? U'minayin She'im
Lo Machal Lo She'hu Achzari? How do you know that if you,
now we're switching sides, this is so much like a יום כיפור
Yom Kippur discussion, right? You have to ask forgiveness and now you
have to you have to be prepared to give forgiveness. You're not
obligated to, but if you're not going to give forgiveness, you're cruel.
שנאמר ויתפלל אברהם אל האלקים וירפא אלקים את אבימלך. She'ne'emar Vayispallel Avraham
El Ha'elokim Vayirpa Elokim Es Avimelech. אברהם Avraham prayed. I don't know
how that shows
that you're cruel if you didn't. I mean, okay, אברהם Avraham was
אברהם. Avraham. You know, why does that mean that if I'm not
acting like אברהם Avraham I'm a cruel person? Not exactly sure what
the evidence is from the פסוק. Pasuk. But in terms of my
question, by the way, so is that was that issue an issue
of shaming? Like it wasn't like אבימלך Avimelech took this woman and
everybody knew אבימלך Avimelech had now, you know, had
now taken שרה, Sarah, אברהם's Avraham wife. Everybody thought it was אברהם's
Avraham sister. There was no public shaming that occurred, right? So, you
know, so the case is not a case of public shaming. So
it is interesting in terms of this question of what is the
scope that the גמרא Gemara thinks is these cases that you have
to ask מחילה, Mechila, yes.
I'll just point out that you know, this is an extension from
what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, even the poorest people in ישראל,
Yisrael, you view them
as if they are בני חורין, Bnei Chorin, בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב.
Bnei Avraham Yitzchak Veyaakov. Ah, בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Bnei Avraham Yitzchak
Veyaakov. That's a nice point too. And that's why maybe we have
to live up to the example of אברהם Avraham about not being
an אכזרי. Achzari. Okay. All right. Very inter... okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, האומר, Ha'omer, now this is a totally different point
to the משנה, Mishnah, which we're not going to get to today.
האומר סמא עיני קטע ידי שבר רגלי חייב. Ha'omer Sima Eini Katas
Yadi Shaver Ragli Chayav. If I say to somebody, you know what?
I ask you, sort of like cutting down my my my saplings.
Blind my eye, sfore, thank you, you know, cut off my hand,
break my leg, then even though I asked you to do it,
you have to pay me. Even if I say, על מנת לפטור,
Al Menas Liftor, do it and I'll exempt you,
חייב. Chayav. However, if I say קרע כסותי שבר כדי, Kares Kesusi
Shaver Kadi, I tell you to you know, tear my clothes, break
my pitcher, חייב. Chayav. Now that's a חידוש, Chiddush, because that's property,
and you would think if I asked you to do it, like
I asked you to cut down the stuff, but if there's no
good if it's not clear that this is the like the tree
that needs to get cut down, it's clear that it's a destructive
act, right? So if I'm asking you to do something which is
a destructive a clearly an act of destroying property, not serving any
purpose, then I'm not giving you, and I think it's a bit
חידוש, Chiddush, I'm not giving you an implicit exemption of of payment,
even if I asked you to do it. But if I say
it explicitly, על מנת לפטור פטור. Al Menas Liftor Patur. If I
say on the condition that you're exempt, then you are exempt. So
this is a big חידוש. Chiddush. Number one, even if I explicitly
exempt you when it comes to injuring me, you're still חייב. Chayav.
Now that might be because I can never really mean it. Okay,
it's never really sincere. How could I really mean to exempt you
if you've done an injury to me? Or it could just mean
that objectively that you know, injury to a person is always objectively
injury. Destruction of property, as we've just seen, is not always destruction.
It depends on the context and the purpose. Okay, so when it
comes to injury of a person, my exempting of you does no
good. When it comes to destroying property, the חידוש Chiddush is that
even if I asked you to do it, that's not enough to
implicitly mean a מחילה Mechila or to implicitly redefine it that it's
not a destructive act. So it's a you know, so it's a
very big חידוש Chiddush that the only time you're exempt is when
it's both property, which can be by context sometimes not seen as
destructive, and when it comes with an explicit exemption, an explicit, you
know, and you won't have to pay. עשה כן לפלוני על מנת
לפטור, Asa Ken Li'ploni Al Menas Liftor, if I say, go beat
up so-and-so, but don't worry, I'll exempt you, so חייב בין בגופו
בין בממונו. Chayav Bein Be'gufo Bein Be'mamono. Go ahead and destroy that
guy's property, it's okay, trust me, you won't have to pay. No,
you still have to pay. Okay, I'm not in a position to
be מוחל. Mochel. I don't have to pay, you do it, so
אין שליח לדבר עבירה. Ein Shliach Li'dvar Aveira. Okay, let's take a
look. Now we have a fun opportunity to דרשן Darshen these פסוקים
Pesukim by אברהם. Avraham. Yes.
Rabbi, why does רשי Rashi on the משנה Mishnah make a point
to say סתם Stam and not according to רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva?
Oh, because the last משנה Mishnah ended with a statement of רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
So we want to make sure that we want...
this is גבי הכל. Gvei Hakol. Yes. תנו רבנן כל אלו שאמרו,
Tanu Rabanan Kol Eilu She'amru, now listen again to the ברייתא. Braisa.
The ברייתא Braisa then... starts with the בושת *Boshet* context. All of
those that they said were that about the values, 200, 100, 400
of the previous משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*, דמי בשתו *d'mei boshto*. That's only
the compensation for the embarrassment. But צער *tza'ar*, the anguish, now this
doesn't mean the physical pain like when it's a חבלה *chavalah*. This
is a scenario of בושת *Boshet*. So the anguish as opposed to
the shame of it, right, אפילו הביא כל אילי נביות שבעולם *afilu
heivi kol eilei nevayot sheba'olam* even if you bring all of the
beautiful rams in the world as קרבנות *korbanot* to God, אין נמחל
לו *ein nimchal lo* God will not be forgiven to you up
in heaven for the sin, עד ad, שיבקש ממנו *ad sheyivakesh mimeno*
until you ask מחילה *mechila* from the person. שנאמר השיב אשת האיש
כי נביא הוא ki navi hu ויתפלל בעדך *Shene'emar hashiv eshet ha'ish
ki navi hu veyitpalel ba'adecha*. Okay, so I want בעדך *ba'adcha*. Okay,
sorry, בעדך *ba'adcha*. I mean, okay. So,
so anyway, so, so here's the question. First of all, I think
it's a really interesting question, right, about what is בושת *Boshet*? We
never really fully explained this. Like, can there be בושת *Boshet* in
private? You know, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* just discusses בושת *Boshet* in
a bathhouse where they were or when you are naked. Right, right,
but well you are ישן *yashen*. Oh no, he was ישן *yashen*
and then he died. Right, but does there have to be other
people around? Let's say you know and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just
discussed the בושת *Boshet* of the family. Let's say you did something
to me in private, nobody else was around, but you still are,
you know, you still like even if nobody else was around, right,
you still...
It's not embarrassment, it's shame. And you can experience shame privately. Shame
and embarrassment are different.
Isn't shame also once you've done something wrong? Can you be ashamed
of yourself? Ashamed of yourself. Well, but anyway, it's a deeper... okay,
so you're saying that if nobody else was around then it's sort
of like the psychological anguish. Somebody called me a mean name or
whatever or they said whatever or they spat in my face. That's
not that's not embarrassment because nobody there's nobody to be embarrassed from.
There's nobody else around. Right. Okay, so that's my sense that the
whole idea of בושת *Boshet* means other people and I think what
the ברייתא *Baraita* here refers to as צער *tza'ar*, the צער *tza'ar*
of the בושת *Boshet* is not the embarrassment, it's the it's the
I don't know if shame is the right word, shame implies something
wrong, but it's the anguish, it's the psychic pain. Yeah, the psychic
pain. What do you want to say, Seth?
Well, shame implies something wrong.
Doesn't it? Can I be ashamed of something if I didn't do
anything wrong?
It's a subjective experience.
I experience it as I've done something wrong. You can't have shame
if you don't experience that you've done something wrong.
Okay, something wrong with you to have...
yeah, but but that's that's too limiting for this. This is psychological
anguish, right? If somebody calls me a name, right, you know, we're
all you know in our minds reliving that experience in grade school
when somebody did something to us or whatever, we live with those
psychological it's not shame. It's not that you know you feel you've
done something wrong, is it? That's what you
experience. I understand. You think that is shame? Dehumanizing. Right. Okay, anyway,
whatever term we have, that's the צער *tza'ar* here. Okay, so the
בושת *Boshet* is the public embarrassment and the צער *tza'ar* is that
anguish and shame and whatever that you carry with you independent of
that, which can sometimes occur even without the public aspect of it.
Okay.
Right, exactly. So that you need forgiveness for. So again the question
I ask is, so if I but if I if I break
my if I if I total Michael's car and pay him for
it I don't have to ask him I don't have to ask
מחילה *mechila* maybe. Maybe if I step on his foot and there's
no shame or embarrassment or anything and I pay him for it,
maybe I don't have to ask him מחילה *mechila*, right? I don't
know, but you know that's not clear what's the context in which
I have to ask him מחילה *mechila*. Okay, let's go back now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues with the אברהם Avraham *Avraham* story. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s now going
to do a דרש *drash* on the פסוקים pesukim, *psukim*. It says
return the man's wife because he's a נביא navi, *navi*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דאשת נביא בעי אהדורי *de'eshet navi ba'ei ahadorei*
the wife of a prophet you have to return. אשת אחר לא
בעי אהדורי *eshet acher lo ba'ei ahadorei* you wouldn't have to return
another man's wife? So אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן
*amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan* no, here's how to
read the פסוק *pasuk*. השיב אשת האיש מכל מקום *hashiv eshet ha'ish
mikol makom* return the man's wife regardless, it's because she's a married
woman. Okay, ודקאמרת הגוי גם צדיק תהרוג *ude'ka'amarta hagoy gam tzaddik taharog*
but you were trying to defend yourself and you were saying God
would you destroy a righteous nation? You know, the guy he told
me it was his wife it was his sister, what did I
do wrong? So הלא הוא אמר לי אחותי היא והיא גם היא
אמרה אחי הוא *halo hu amar li achoti hi vehi gam hi
amra achi hu* everybody said sister, brother. So God said back נביא
הוא *navi hu* he's a prophet which somehow means like he knows
what your real intention is or God knows what your real intention
is. ודכבר לימא *ud'kvar leima* now our version here is he's already
taught but but the version of this in מכות *Makkot* is ודכבר
למד ממך *ud'kvar lamad mimcha* he's learned from you. Okay, and let's
see what it is that either he taught or he learned from
you. אכסנאי שבא לעיר *achsana'i sheba le'ir* when a visitor comes to
the city על עסקי אכילה ושתיה שואלין אותו *al iskei achila u'shtiya
sho'alin oto* do you say to him oh do you have a
place to sleep, a place a place where you're staying, can we
provide food for you? You know או על עסקי אשה שואלין אותו
*o al iskei isha sho'alin oto* or do you ask of him
hey what's the story with that woman traveling with you? Right? אשתך
היא אחותך היא *ishtecha hi achotecha hi* is that your wife? Is
that your sister? So it depends on... who's teaching whom. The version
in מכות says, "Hey, buddy, Avraham figured out the fact that you're
asking about his wife, is it his wife, is it his sister,
it's very clear what your intentions were. Your intentions were not so
pure, you know, what type of... clearly, you know, if you're totally
pure, you don't start asking about the woman that somebody is traveling
with. The other version is a harder version to understand, which is,
from the story earlier with Avraham and Sarah with Pharaoh, you should
have learned that what? You should have learned that when somebody goes
around with a woman and says it's a sister, it might be
his wife? I mean, that's a little interesting. Anyway, but somehow the
point is, he's a נביא, you should have learned from him, you
know, or he knows that your intentions were not so pure. Okay,
מכאן לבן נח שנהרג שהיה לו ללמוד ולא למד. mikan l'ven Noach
shenehreg shehaya lo lilmod v'lo lamad. And from here, because God was
prepared to kill him, you know, it sounds like... I mean, although
it doesn't sound like kill, it was like, you know, עצר עצר
השם בעד כל רחם. atzar atzar Hashem baad kol rechem. But anyway,
but you see that he was deserving of death and he can't
claim ignorance. Okay, now what can he not claim ignorance of? Ignorance
of the law or ignorance of the facts? So, you know, to
what he was really ignorant of was the facts, that it was
his wife rather than his sister. So really? Like you can't be
exempt if you did some questions or whatever... I mean, you know,
or can you say, well, I didn't know it was אסור assur
to commit adultery? That was never the discussion, whether it was אסור
assur to commit adultery, right? So it's... I really don't know how
to fully unpack this גמרא. Gemara But somehow it sounds like he
should have figured out from your precedents with Pharaoh, or your questions
made it obvious that your intentions were not so pure, that you
cannot really claim pure innocence of knowledge and pure innocence of, you
know, of not knowing the facts. You had a responsibility to know
the facts better, you know, either because you should have learned from
what Avraham did by Pharaoh, which is very funny, I should have
learned from this other person's misdeeds and lying in a previous case
not to trust him now, right? Or if your intentions were not
so pure, you have a responsibility to do more due diligence. Okay,
and even so you'll be held liable for your actions. Yes.
Is this a situation where Avraham says there's no יראת שמים yirat
shamayim here, specifically?
Does that have any note? Right. Right. And that's... and that's where
this מדרש Midrash is. How do you know there's no יראת שמים?
yirat shamayim? That רש"י Rashi brings that in in a better place.
Bringing this in in כי נביא הוא doesn't fit so well. What
does that have to do with him being a prophet? But it
does... it is a very good gloss on רק אין יראת אלוהים
במקום הזה. rak ein yirat Elokim bamakom hazeh. What are they doing
asking about this woman I'm traveling with? Okay, yeah. All right, so
now the גמרא continues. כי עצור עצר השם. ki atzor atzar Hashem.
God had closed up, you know, בעד כל רחם, baad kol rechem,
literally every womb. But the question is even in the פסוקים, pesukim.
does that mean womb or is that a euphemism? Orifice, not general
orifice, but it basically means it was impossible to have sex, okay?
So, you know, it's referring to the vagina, not the womb. So
that's I think just a פשט pshat question in the פסוקים. pesukim
But let's see what the גמרא does. אמר רבי אלעזר שתי עצירו
הללו למה? amar Rabbi Elazar shtei atzirot hallalu lamah? So what are
the purpose of these two closings, עצור עצר? atzor atzar? אחת באיש,
achat ba'ish, so both men and women had their orifices closed, or
at least their sexual organs or orifices. אחת באיש שכבת זרע, achat
ba'ish shichvat zera, he couldn't ejaculate.
שתיים באשה שכבת זרע ולידה. shtayim ba'ishah shichvat zera v'leidah. She could
not... now שכבת זרע shichvat zera here could mean, I would think
it means that she could not receive sperm, and it means that
they couldn't have sex. But רש"י Rashi says it means had sperm
gone into her body, it won't come out, which I don't really
understand what the purpose of that is of emphasizing that. And she
couldn't give birth.
במתניתא תנא שתיים באיש.
bemattnita tana
shtayim ba'ish.
Go to the bathroom.
Right. במתניתא תנא, bemattnita tana, thank you for anticipating that, שתיים באיש,
shtayim ba'ish, two for men, שכבת זרע וקטנים, shichvat zera u'ktanim, he
couldn't urinate also. שלוש באשה שכבת זרע וקטנים ולידה. shalosh ba'ishah shichvat
zera u'ktanim v'leidah. She couldn't... whether that means in or out, וקטנים,
u'ktanim, and she couldn't urinate, ולידה, v'leidah, and she couldn't give birth.
Once we're... now they're on a roll. רבינא אמר שלוש באיש שכבת
זרע וקטנים ופי הטבעת. Ravina amar shalosh ba'ish shichvat zera u'ktanim u'fi
hataba'at.
He also couldn't defecate. ארבע באשה
שכבת זרע ולידה וקטנים ופי
הטבעת. arba ba'ishah shichvat zera v'leidah u'ktanim u'fi hataba'at. Okay, all the
orifices were closed. Okay, בעד כל רחם, baad kol rechem, for every
womb. אמרי דבי רבי ינאי אפילו תרנגולת של בית אבימלך לא הטילה
ביצתה. amrei d'vei Rabbi Yannai afilu tarnegolet shel beit Avimelech lo hetilah
beitzatah. Even the... even the chickens, even the hens in the house
of Avimelech did not drop their eggs during that time. אמר ליה
רבא לרבה בר מרי. amar lei Rava l'Rabba bar Mari. So now
we're going to have a whole rest of the דף daf talking
about where do we have biblical precedents for common sayings, okay? So
for common, you know, popular... popular sayings. So אמר ליה רבא לרבה
בר מרי מנא הא מילתא דאמרי רבנן, amar lei Rava l'Rabba bar
Mari mna ha milta d'amri rabanan, where does this... what's the basis
for this things that the Rabbis say? And first we... I'm sorry,
first we do rabbinic sayings and then we're going to talk about
popular sayings. What's the basis for this things that the Rabbis say?
כל המבקש רחמים על חבירו והוא צריך לאותו דבר הוא נענה תחילה.
kol
hamevakesh
rachamim al chaveiro v'hu tzarich l'oto davar hu ne'eneh techilah. Anybody who
prays for his friend but you're in need of the thing you're
praying for, right, then you're answered first. If you act selflessly, then,
you know, your needs somehow will be... will be taken care of.
אמר ליה דכתיב וה' שב את שבות איוב בהתפללו בעד רעהו. amar
lei d'chtiv v'Hashem shav et shevut Iyov b'hitpalalo baad re'eihu.
God returned, you know, the captivity of Iyov when he prayed for
his friends. Iyov was praying for his friends and Iyov was answered
first for himself. אמר ליה את אמרת מהתם ואנא אמינא מהכא. amar
lei at amart meihatam v'ana amina meihacha. You say from there, you
went all the way to Iyov, and
I'm going to tell you from here, from... ויתפלל אברהם אל האלקים
Vayispallel Avraham el ha'Elokim וירפא אלקים את אבימלך Vayirpa Elokim es Avimelech
אבימלך Avimelech got healed ואת אשתו ואמהותיו וילדו ve'es ishto ve'amosav vayeledu
וכתיב uksiv וד' פקד את שרה VaHashem pakad es Sarah כאשר אמר.
ka'asher amar.
Now the דרשה drashah here is it's
not—he had already פקד pakad את שרה, es Sarah, that's the דרשה,
drashah, right. כאשר אמר, ka'asher amar, כאשר אמר אברהם. ka'asher amar Avraham.
Now, when Abraham said על אבימלך, al Avimelech,
when אברהם Avraham had prayed על אבימלך, al Avimelech, not as God
had said but according to אברהם's Avraham, request for אבימלך, Avimelech, God
had answered Sarah at that moment. Okay, so אמר
ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי. Amar lei Rava le-Rabbah bar Mari. Although
if you think about it, that's a little bit problematic because Abraham
would have had to have had sex with her
after he—you gotta make sure it's Abraham's baby, what? אין מוקדם
ומאוחר בתורה.
Ein mukdam u-meuchar
ba-Torah. No, no, no, I'm just saying think about the sequence. אבימלך
Avimelech takes Sarah, he returns her to אברהם, Avraham and אברהם is
praying for אבימלך Avimelech and Sarah is becoming—is conceiving. Conceiving from what
event? Right, no. Or maybe before—maybe before she was taken by אבימלך.
Avimelech. Okay, fine. Anyway, okay.
גנבת סוסים אצל רשב"ם בתוספות. Ganavat susim etzel Rashbam be-Tosafot.
Yeah, I know, but that's what people were saying, but I'm just
saying according to the actual facts the way the גמרא's laying it
out. By the way, one of
the—it's always fun looking at the way like Rabbinic sort of insults
or, you know, a way they sort of, you know, like, like,
like, sharp comments when they're, when they're having like these arguments לשם
שמים. le-shem shamayim. So anyway, one of them that I really appreciated
was, there was a ט"ז Taz who was sort of quoting some
opinion, I think it was the ב"ח, Bach, and anyway he said
like ושרא ליה מאריה, v'shara lei marei, which means like, you know,
the רבונו של עולם Ribbono shel Olam should forgive him for saying
such a stupid thing. So then the ש"ך Shach says about the
ט"ז, Taz, יתפלל על אחרים והוא צריך לאותו דבר. Yispallel al acherim
ve-hu tzarich l'oso davar. He prayed for other people but he's the
one who needed that prayer, like he's saying the stupid things. Anyway,
fine. Okay.
So גמרא says, all right, where are we?
Okay. כאשר אמר אברהם אל אבימלך. Ka'asher amar Avraham el Avimelech. אמר
ליה רבא לרבה בר
מרי. Amar lei Rava le-Rabbah bar Mari. מנא הא מילתא דאמרי אינשי.
Mena ha milta de'amri inshi.
Now we go from a Rabbinic saying to a popular saying. What's
the basis in the תורה Torah for the popular saying בהדי הוצא
לקי כרבא? be'hadei hutza laki karba?
When you're together with the vine, the
actual vegetable is also injured. Like when you have to uproot the
weeds, sometimes you wind up uprooting the vegetable together with the weeds.
So, אמר ליה דכתיב: amar lei deksiv: למה תריבו אלי כולכם? lama
tarivu elai kulchem? And למה תריבו אלי, lama tarivu elai, why are
you fighting against me? כולכם פשעתם בי, kulchem pashatem bi, you've all
sinned against me, נאום ד'. neum Hashem. So, including the צדיקים tzaddikim
together with the רשעים. reshaim. אמר ליה את אמרת מהתם, Amar lei
at amarta me'hatam,
you're saying from there, ואנא אמינא מהכא. va'ana amina me'hacha. אד אנה
מאנתם, Ad ana me'antem, like it's clear רבא Rava wants to go
back to the פסוקים in the תורה. Torah. אד אנה מאנתם לשמור
מצותי ותורותי. Ad ana me'antem lishmor mitzvosai ve-sorosai.
To when have you refused? God is saying to משה Moshe and
אהרן Aharon and He's talking about all of בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
but He's including משה Moshe and אהרן. Aharon. How long have they—have
they refused to observe my מצוות? mitzvos? Are you all refusing to
observe my
מצוות? mitzvos? אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי: Amar lei Rava le-Rabbah
bar Mari: כתיב ומקצה אחיו לקח חמשה אנשים. ksiv u-miketze achav lakach
chamisha anashim. The verse says, and from the קצה katze of his
brothers he took five people.
יוסף Yosef took five of his brothers from the קצה, katze, which
רש"י Rashi interprets it means from the weaker of his brothers so
that פרעה Paroh should not, you know, should not try to take
him for פרעה's Paroh own, you know, shepherds and so on. So
he took five people. So מן אינהו חמשה? man inhu chamisha? Who
are these five, which of the five brothers? אמר ליה הכי אמר
רב יוחנן: Amar lei hachi amar Rav Yochanan: אותם שהוכפלו בשמות. osam
she-huchpelu bi-shemos. If you read in the ברכה, beracha, you know,
that—what do you call it? You know, in the ברכה beracha in
וזאת הברכה, Vezos Haberacha, five of the brothers their names are repeated,
okay. ולשמעון אמר, ve-li-Shimon amar, you know, ולדן אמר, ve-li-Dan amar, דן
גור אריה. Dan gur aryeh. So it repeats the names. And the
others it doesn't repeat the names. So the דרשה drashah here is,
the way רש"י Rashi explains it, the five whose names are repeated—what?
וזאת הברכה. Vezos Haberacha.
Oh, that's וזאת הברכה, Vezos Haberacha, excuse me, not ויחי. Vayichi. That's
what I was trying to think of as I was talking. Yeah,
you're right, it is
וזאת הברכה. Vezos Haberacha. Excuse me. Right. Because it's—yeah, yeah, yeah. You're
right, it's וזאת הברכה, Vezos Haberacha, right. Thank you. Okay. It's וזאת
הברכה. Vezos Haberacha. So in וזאת הברכה, Vezos Haberacha, five of the
names are repeated, and רש"י Rashi says that's an indication that they
were weaker, so they needed the repetition of the names in order
to like give them, you know, the strength. So and therefore because
they were the weaker brothers, they were the ones that יוסף Yosef
took and stood before פרעה. Paroh. Okay. So it says like this:
אותם שהוכפלו בשמות. osam she-huchpelu bi-shemos. So גמרא says, one minute, they're
not five, they are six. יהודה נמי איכפול מיכפל. Yehuda nami ichpul
michpal. יהודה Yehuda was also repeated and clearly יהודה Yehuda is not
a weaker brother, you know, he was the strong one. So how
does this work out, and it's six and it's not five? אמר
ליה למילתא הוא דאיכפל. Amar lei le-milta hu de'ichpal. No, no, no.
יהודה. Yehuda. was repeated for a different purpose, not because he was
weaker, but for a different דרשה. drasha. דאמר רבי יוחנן משמיה דרבי
שמעון בר יוחאי, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishmeih d'Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, מאי
דכתיב, mai d'ksiv, what's meant, יחי ראובן, yechi Reuven, right? It's the
וזאת הברכה. v'Zos HaBracha. יחי ראובן ואל ימות, yechi Reuven v'al yamot,
ראובן Reuven should live and not die, ויהי מתיו מספר, v'yehi misav
mispar, his men should be numbered, וזאת ליהודה. v'zos l'Yehuda. So what
is the וזאת ליהודה v'zos l'Yehuda mean? Right, the other repetitions are
לדן אמר, l'Dan amar, right, לאשר אמר, l'Asher amar, what's וזאת ליהודה?
v'zos l'Yehuda? So here's the דרשה drasha and that's why it's said
twice. כל אותן ארבעים שנה שהיו ישראל במדבר, kol osan arbaim shana
shehayu Yisrael bammidbar, the forty years that they were in the wilderness,
היו עצמותיו של יהודה מגולגלים בארון. hayu atzmosav shel Yehuda m'gulgaliym ba'aron.
יהודה's Yehuda bones were rolling in the ארון, aron, they were not
at rest and they were... Rashi says that the skeleton was not
whole, all the bones had all sort of, you know, fallen out
of the structure. Okay, עד, and the reason is because יהודה Yehuda
said to his father וחטאתי לאבי כל הימים. v'chatasi l'avi kol hayamim.
So if I don't return בנימין. Binyamin. And the point is
even though he did return בנימין, Binyamin, right, since you know... so
Rashi quotes a גמרא that says a curse of a sage, even
if it's on a condition, is still effective. So even though he
brought, you know, he said about himself and even though the condition
was met, there was still some impact of saying that. So therefore
it had not somehow fully been released from that. עד שבא משה
וביקש רחמים, ad sheba Moshe u'vikeish rachamim, until משה Moshe came and
prayed for יהודה. Yehuda. אמר לפניו רבונו של עולם, amar lefanav Ribono
shel olam, מי גרם לראובן שיודה? mi garam l'Reuven she'yodeh? Who caused
ראובן Reuven to admit for his sin of sleeping with his father's
maidservant? יהודה. Yehuda. Because that's another דרשה, drasha, that when יהודה Yehuda
sort of said, you know, צדקה ממני, tzadka mimeni, so ראובן Reuven
said, 'Oh my God, יהודה Yehuda now admitted to what he had
done with תמר, Tamar, I have to admit to my
sin.'
I don't know if he actually admitted anything. מיד שמע ה' קול
יהודה. miyad shma Hashem kol Yehuda. So meaning the way the דרשה
drasha is, is that משה Moshe is saying you just finished talking
about ראובן Reuven and then after praising ראובן, Reuven, משה Moshe is
saying וזאת ליהודה? v'zos l'Yehuda? So, you know, given ראובן Reuven and
ראובן Reuven admitted whatever, this is for יהודה's Yehuda sake? That his
bones are, you know, rolling around in the ארון? aron? יהודה Yehuda
was the cause for ראובן Reuven having admitted. So מיד שמע ה'
קול יהודה. miyad shma Hashem kol Yehuda. So God heard the voice,
or God should hear, but God did hear the voice of יהודה
Yehuda and God responded to משה. Moshe. על איבריה לשפא. al eivarei
l'shafa. So the limbs, the bones went into their sockets. Okay, so
they stopped rolling around, the structure got reconstructed. But nevertheless, לא הוו
קא מעיילי ליה למתיבתא דרקיעא, lo havu ka m'ayeili leh limsivta d'rakiya,
but יהודה Yehuda still was not invited to the בית מדרש beis
medrash up in שמים. Shamayim. Okay, even though his bones got fixed.
So משה Moshe continued to pray. ואל עמו תביאנו, v'el amo t'vienu,
let him come into his nation, his nation is clearly the בית
מדרש beis medrash up in heaven. ולא הוה ידע מאי קאמרי רבנן,
v'lo hava yada mai ka'amri rabanan, but it was like the story
about, you know, משה Moshe in the בית מדרש beis medrash of
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so he was entered into the בית מדרש
beis medrash but he didn't know what the conversations were about. למישקל
ולמיטרח בהדי רבנן, l'mishkal u'l'mitrach bahadi rabanan, he didn't know how to
have good halachic discussions with the רבנן rabanan there. ידיו רב לו,
yadav rav lo, let his hands be victorious for him, let him
have ability to argue in the בית מדרש. beis medrash. ולא הוה
סליק ליה שמעתתא אליבא דהלכתא, v'lo hava salik leh shma'ata aliba d'hilchasa,
fine, he was able to argue but he never... his argument never
won out, we never פוסק pasken like him. ועזר מצריו תהיה, v'ezer
mitzrav tihyeh, let him have strength against his adversaries. Okay, so very
fascinating how we went from יהודה Yehuda now to being a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham in a בית מדרש beis medrash up in שמים.
Shamayim. But anyway, now we're going to go back to popular sayings.
Let's just see if we can turn the page. Okay. אמר ליה
רבא לרבה בר מרי, amar leh Rava l'Rabbah bar Mari, מנא הא
מילתא דאמרי אינשי? m'na ha milta d'amri inshi? Where's this thing that
people say, בתר עניא אזלא עניותא? basar anya azla anyusa? Right, like
we would say the rich get richer and the poor get poorer,
poverty follows... follows the poor. אמר ליה דתנן, amar leh d'tnan, we
have a משנה.
עשירים מביאים בכורים בסלים של זהב ושל כסף, ashirim mevi'im bikurim b'salim
shel zahav v'shel kesef, the עשירים ashirim would bring their בכורים bikurim
in like these baskets of gold and silver. ועניים, v'aniym, and the
poor, מביאים בכורים בסלי נצרים של ערבה קלופה, mevi'im bikurim b'salei netzarim
shel arava klupha, they would bring it in like these, like, wicker
baskets of like peeled, you know, whatever wicker, whatever. והסלים והבכורים ניתנים
לכהנים, v'hasalim v'habikurim nitanim l'kohanim, when you would give it to the
כהנים, kohanim, so if you were giving it in a poor wicker
basket, the כהנים kohanim would keep the basket. If you gave it
in a nice gold or silver basket, they would return the basket.
So the poor person, he has to give his basket as well.
Exactly, they add even poorer. Exactly, they add even poor, they even
have to give up their basket, the rich ones don't give up
their basket. אמר ליה את אמרת מהתם amar leh at amart meihasam
ואנא אמינא מהכא, v'ana amina meihacha, I say from here. וטמא טמא
יקרא. v'tamay tamay yikra. So the... the מצורע metzora is kicked out
of the camp and then he has to tell everybody, 'I'm טמא,
tamay, I'm טמא, tamay, keep away from me.' So it's not enough
that he's been pushed out, he has to push himself even further
out. Which is not exactly about poverty. All right, let's read one
more line. I know it's already over, but we'll read one more
line. אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי, amar leh Rava l'Rabbah bar
Mari, מנא הא מילתא דאמרי רבנן? m'na ha milta d'amri rabanan? Where's
this thing the רבנן rabanan say, השכם ואכול בקיץ מפני החמה ובחורף
מפני הצינה?
hashkeim v'echol bakayitz mipnei hachama u'vachoref mipnei
hatzina? Right, yeah, exactly, to figure out how these also match up
to Ben Franklin sayings. Where do you know people say, you know,
eat early in the
morning? Sixty people can run after somebody and they won't catch up
to a person who has his bread in the morning. So how
do you know the importance of a good breakfast? So אמר ליה
amar lei so he says דכתיב dichtiv לא ירעבו ולא יצמאו ולא
יכם שרב ושמש. lo yir'avu v'lo yitzmau v'lo yakeim sharav vashamesh. They
will not be hungry and they will not be thirsty and the
heat and the sun will not hit them. So meaning if you
eat early and you're not hungry then you won't be affected by
other things. אמר ליה amar lei אנת אמרת מהתם ant amrat meihatam
you say there ואנא אמינא מהכא va'ana amina meihacha
ועבדתם את ה' אלהיכם va'avadtam et Hashem Elokeichem you should serve Hashem
your God זו קריאת שמע ותפילה zu k'riat shema u'tfilah that's the
davening וברך את לחמך ואת מימיך u'veirach et lachmecha v'et meimecha
and then He will bless your bread and your water so that's
your breakfast 'cause you can't eat till you daven זו פת במלח
וקיתון של מים zu pat bemelach vekiton shel mayim your bread and
salt and also some water and מכאן ולהלן mikan u'leihalan והסירותי מחלה
מקרבך vahasiroti machalah mikirbecha
I will remove all sickness from you once you have your good
morning breakfast you won't be sick. דתניא d'tanya מחלה זו מרה machalah
zu marah מחלה machalah is gall or bile. Okay. ולמה נקרא שמה
מחלה? v'lamah nikra shemah machalah? Why is it called מחלה? machalah? ששמונים
ושלושה חלאים יש בה sheshmonim ushloshah cholayim yesh bah because in gall
and bile there are 83 types of sickness because מחלה בגימטריא הכי
הוי machalah b'gematriya hachi havei that's the gematria of מחלה. machalah. וכולן
v'chulan all these bad things that can be brought on by by
gall or bile פת במלח שחרית וקיתון של מים מבטלתן. pat bemelach
shacharit vekiton shel mayim mevateltan.
If you have a if you just have some bread in the
morning you'll be safe from all of these afflictions. Okay to be
continued tomorrow.